I thought uh you'd like to see the
ancient book for D1 okay and look you
don't have to worry much about the
ancient language uh but it's a good seat
in your mind for the future okay so just
relax and you can look at it you don't
have to worry
[Music]
much
yeah and um H to that
[Music]
quite
said so uh we can kind of look at it
together uh the first one is called say
[Music]
say and you don't have to learn it in
this lifetime okay
I'm planting seeds for next
time I'll meet we have a date okay for
next
life does he need to do something was
giving me some
instructions okay don't move my head
when I talk without instruction all
right we will not do it okay so Tang
means uh start out with equal towards
all
[Music]
people and that's difficult like our
family naturally we care more about
[Music]
them so it's it's very difficult to be
equal to
[Music]
anybody okay Second
Step uh say mar
mar uh 50 years
ago I went to my first
class in the
Himalayas and uh I had to pass an
examination to get into
the and the Llama who was teaching
translating the
class he he was my
neighbor and he wanted me to get into
the
club but I didn't know
any and actually it was shant it was a
class
[Music]
about and but I have to take entrance
examination so there's a board of three
llamas very high this one is
[Music]
he's and he said are you ready for your
exam he promised me I don't have to
worry but actually I don't know
[Music]
anything then he said okay please
translate this Tibetan
word okay okay okay Mama Mama I'm like
mom mama
good and then Papa Papa said Dad papa
papa good you
passed so here here the m mom is as the
mother as your
mother sh means to to know that other
people have been your
[Music]
mother okay
uh the next line has the name of a nice
book in it who can
get
K say
k yeah kin means the kindness of your
teacher or the kindness of your
[Music]
mom and we wrote a I wrote a book in my
threeyear
retreat and it's called
K and it means the kindness of my
teacher and the teacher when I was in
high school who taught me how to
write she's a old grumpy lady named
[Music]
Catherine but she taught me to
write for two years and so I secretly I
put her name on the
book and it's
K so here it says tin
say
chin chin means remember the kindness of
your
mother every person in this
room has I this is weird Okay Jose this
is a little bit
strange I also gave you milk from my
breath and you also gave me milk
it's a little strange okay but you got
to get used to
it all of us gave milk to each
other and uh each one of us is part of
each other
person because we gave our body to each
[Music]
other and just think about it
sometimes
mathematically it's certain that we did
that because time is
infinite and you cannot kill the human
[Music]
mind you can stop the
blood you can kill the
flesh but the human mind is independent
of
this and it has lived forever
okay so Jose don't forget all
right all right then he added something
here
say yeah it means says special
kindness and uh 35
years we are saving the ancient books of
Asia
I'll give you
example so Harvard University has the
biggest collection of Western classic
books in the
world uh Western
yeah and then uh it's 530
books how many
sorry
[Music]
Yeah in our
tradition it's
300,000 okay and they are spread all
over the
[Music]
world in strange libraries in the
Himalayas and
[Music]
everywhere so for 35 years uh we are
working to find
them John Brady's in Mongolia right now
I
think and finding more books
okay then we photograph
them then then we inut
them and we have a big group of refugees
in India they are inputting for three
generations now
[Music]
Brady has finished 12 million
pages and it's online for
free then uh so he says something
strange
here he says uh remember the kindness of
Jose
and then remember his special
kindness so I I I if I don't know what's
a special
kindness I can search in the I can
search in the
database in two
seconds I can search 12 million
pages and what it say said
was when we say special kindness maybe
it means that Jose has been my L
before and I have been your llama we
have been each other's
llama and after this life we we don't
know who's going to be the Llama you or
me that's why I have to make sure they
make good coffee for the
Llama it might be you it might be
me okay and that's one way to understand
special but it also means uh when you
think about kindness of your
teacher
the special teacher is everybody that
you ever meet
okay every everyone around you has is
your
teacher now
uh I have to say one thing about guara
group uh how many years ago 30 years ago
I say how many
30 uh I started to teach uh what we call
Diamond
way uh and this is a way to become
Buddha in one
life uh and I taught it for 14
years uh uh and then I graduate about 50
people
and then I I'm I was waiting for a
second
group and I waited about 10 years I
think and then uh it
came and it's from this city called gu
gu
guadara yes
[Applause]
and uh I'd like to thank all the ACI
teachers Tim and other teachers John jig
Gil the other teachers teaching
dyam and uh they're teaching the godart
team like older
[Laughter]
students Diamond
way and there also some students from
Europe and other
places but I'm very grateful and I'd
like to give them a
[Music]
hint
and that uh teaching Diamond way to
somebody is the special kindness
here okay uh step number
four and here's the
Tibetan uh say
chin yeah chin means cting chin signif K
kindness so means to pay it
back okay so that's step number
four and
then means uh this is the
foundation see first start equal equal
thoughts about
everybody
understand they've been your
mother understand they gave you milk and
all the other
things and then try to pay them
back okay that's the
foundation and here it says samj samj
means start with that foundation and
then go go
forther uh now now say another thing say
d hey you guys got to wake
up by the way why we do so
early if we start at 7 o'cl it's it's
10:00 in Asia at night at
night
so we are spreading out the
suffering they have to stay up late you
have to get up
early and it's the only way to teach
everybody at the same
time I think uh teaching from recording
is a little bit
boring so we have to get up early they
have to stay up late
unfortunately Columbus proved the world
is
wrong all right uh so number number
five say
d this is called
uh this is a famous famous uh from
Master Shanti DEA
famous idea from Master
[Music]
shant and
uh sometimes we say uh what do you call
it sometimes they they call it a wrong
name in
English this
idea exchanging self and
others sometimes they call it exchanging
yourself and others
and that's a
misation it's actually two different
ideas it's
called means uh
[Music]
equal and then
exchange okay so what's the
difference okay the first part
equal it's the same as the first step in
the
11 uh the first step is try to treat
everybody
[Laughter]
equally it doesn't mean treat everybody
equally bad it means treat equally
good
yeah okay then uh number five is a
little bit
different and number five it's not so
much that you treat everybody
equally it's that everybody has an equal
right to be
happy nobody has more right to be happy
than somebody
else
and I'm thinking a lot about the the
wars nowadays going
on I think if you have this number five
thought it's impossible to have a
war we all have equal right to be
happy it's not a one country has more
right and one country has less right
that's
[Music]
strange
we all have equal right to be
happy and that's number
five so number five is what they call
exchanging self and others but that's a
Mist
transation it's two
steps number one everybody has equal
right to
happiness
and if you don't uh master that one
first you canot go to the second one
okay so first you have to agree everyone
has equal right to be
him by the way in number five you don't
have to do anything
yet just mentally inside of your own
self uh admit and accept that everyone
has equal right to
have then go to number
[Music]
six it
means
dangen dzen means
there was a book in in America like 10
years ago maybe can't remember I don't
know it's called watching out for number
one taking care of number
one and it was like number one book
selling book in
America you know you have to take care
of yourself
first that's the complete opposite of
this can goate means look try to
understand that taking care of yourself
first it causes you hundreds of problems
in your
life trying to
understand when you try to take
everything first I should be
first I should get the churos
first why gesla doesn't learn Spanish
and
Chinese he just learns the words for
donut
p
so number six
means try to understand how many
problems come from taking care of
yourself
first by the way this is the essence of
all the time all the money all the
effort we did to come here
the purpose to have L
class and it's a tremendous amount of
work for Tim and other
people it's like and why you spent your
money to come
[Music]
here from or
wherever
all of the money we spend all the time
we
spend is for one
thing uh by the time we leave this
beautiful
place at least we should think maybe
taking care of myself first cre some
problem to
me
and that's if if you seriously have that
thought in your
mind maybe taking care of myself first
gave me trouble in my life
maybe then you had a successful
Retreat okay that's all if it just
happen I don't know if you go to
lunch and you start to grab the first
kiss and then you say oh no you
think or you think about why it's a
problem to take the the first
one if you hesitate for one
second then you have a successful
retreat
okay CU it plants a Unstoppable seed in
your
mind later you be able to give your
arm to another person but it starts
withad okay and uh if you have that
thought maybe I shouldn't take the first
one then you had a successful Retreat
already and the rest is just
dessert all right uh so number
six think about how much trouble came in
your life by taking care of yourself
first by the way it's human nature to
take care of yourself
first why
we live in a we call a broken world this
is a broken
[Music]
World once you come to this world your
ass is in
trouble once you're in a human
body you're already going to have
trouble cuz they will fall
apart
I did this stupid yoga for how many
years 24
years 2
24 because I want to look like
anaton but still uh your body will fall
apart doesn't matter you do yoga I mean
yoga will make it slow
down
but we all of us our our body will fall
apart so once we are in this
world uh that's a sign that what brought
us to this world is a
[Music]
problem if you go to a world where your
body has to
die
you must have made some mistake
before okay the result the punishment is
you have to live in a body which will
fall
apart then the cause must have happened
before
that and we can't see it we can't
remember
you can see it with
your third
eye third eye is
Led if if they put me in the jail this
life maybe I did something last
night okay that's called third
eye that's
logic what did I do then I went to the
gym
then you have to look at your most Basic
Instincts in this
[Music]
life and the most Basic Instinct of a
human
baby is to take care ofs
first you know they will try to get the
milk
first human nature okay it's a sign of
of where we came
from and the whole purpose of
Dharma is to fight that human
nature because that human nature brought
you uh I call it a rental car this is a
rental
[Music]
car
when I go to visit my mom
stepmother I fly to San
Diego I rent a car I drive it
around I have to take it back and then I
I have to give it
back so this is a rental
car by the way you only get one in this
l
you can't say I don't like the SUV can
you give me a sports
[Laughter]
car you get stuck with one by your
mom and then by the way you have to take
care of
it it's G to fall apart
anyway okay hair will fall
out and you know all kinds of things
will
happen
but you need your rental
car otherwise you can't do
anything so it's a big part of these
programs learn how to do
yoga or learn how to eat
well and then slow slow down the
breaking of the rental car as far as
possible
because you need
it to to get out of this world you need
to be in this
world and I don't mean that life is all
suffering in the diamond
[Music]
way I'll give you the essence of the
diamond if
if time is
infinite then
logically if time is
infinite and if I can come to this world
one
time I must have been here a billion
times because infinite is very
long it's like if you throw the dce
infinite
times is it possible you throw the dice
and the dice fall exactly right to stay
on the point of
the I mean it's
possible if it's possible once it's
possible a billion
times okay so I have I have been here
here the the dice landed on the chip and
stayed there balanced
countless how many rental cars I I took
in my in my
lives it's
endless then how many rental cars did
you
pay
endless
maybe there's people around
us who already became
Buddha the dice landed on the on the
[Music]
tip
mathematically it's probably
true that there are some spies in this
group bu
spies Budd and uh we don't know who they
are sometimes the Buddha tries to piss
you
off so you can
improve if the if the person who piss
you off very possibly
Buddha
then we got to be
careful okay we got to be nice to
everybody we don't know who's
Buddha by the way the Buddha try to look
like not
[Music]
Buddha the most irritating person in
your life is more
probably
okay uh so number six
is just try to understand there's a lot
of problems when you take the first
TR it's human nature to take the first
one it's human nature that I should be
first but that human nature didn't
work that human nature brought you this
rental
C and this one is
broken if it didn't break yet it's
breaking
okay if you don't have cancer yet just
try to live a little longer you can get
it
okay that's nature of this
body by the way when you get the cancer
you can't get out of the rental car
you're stuck in the rental
car it's like you got in the rental car
and all the doors
[Laughter]
[Music]
go and you have to stay here until it's
finished Okay so
to
[Music]
summarize being stuck in
this breakable rental
car the punishment to live in this
body it must have had some bad cause I
must have done
something and it's is the habit of
taking care of myself
first and the purpose of this
Retreat all the hard work to come
here is just to fight that
habit and if you fight it for two
minutes at lunch after
this if there's one churo left and
there's two people
waiting and you're like look over
there you know then you have if you
hesitate look over
it if if you just hesitate for 10
seconds
then that that will break that habit
later you're are planting the seed to
destroy that
behavior when you hesitate and then you
take the first the last TR
yourself all the money and trouble and
work that we spent to get
[Music]
here
if you hesitate for 10
seconds before you take the last one
yourself you had a successful
ret because it's not human
nature our nature is to take the first
[Music]
one and your whole life your whole
Dharma life you have to fight that
habit
number
seven it is so fun to fight that
habit okay and then suddenly you
discover what is
Joy how much fun it is to give the first
one to somebody
else and I I hope the llamas bless
us to feel that joy in our Liv
I give the first one to
you and then that's total
joy and your whole life will be
fun just get the
Habit here you take the first
one you take the first one
oh there's nothing left for
you yeah that's
cool you know and you just get so
happy and it's such a joy then your then
your life in the jail becomes a
joy then just take care of other people
first but guess what if I don't get
enough what if there's no more churos in
the
kitchen God don't you understand that
comes from taking the first one in the
past it's crazy talk you know czy if I
give away children to everybody I won't
have
that's true but that's kind because you
didn't give away the first one in the
past if you don't like CH don't give to
other
people keep it for
yourself then you will never have more
chur got it and it's so fun to give to
other people
okay
totally your whole life will be fun if
you
try there's a small time
Gap and then the Cho tsunami comes back
to
you everyone banging on your door gu you
need
[Laughter]
some a small time
Gap after you start learning this Habit
to give the first one to other
people and then stuff comes
too and I'm not bragging
okay but why I have $100 bills coming
out of my
backpack I I learned the
secret give them as fast as you
can then the tsunami
come okay really and it's
fun okay that's the best thing it's fun
to give away $100
bill okay and then the more you give the
more they
come j came to my room
yesterday she's like is everything think
is everything okay you seem upset
[Music]
yesterday yeah I said I was a little bit
upset
yesterday because uh I don't know
where's my bank
account I have all these bank accounts I
don't know the number I don't know the
bank I don't know the
password
she took guar group to diamond mountain
on a one month Retreat I don't know how
to get $5 out of my bank
account it's a good
problem okay
so this Retreat is success
if you just try once to give the first
thing to somebody
else there are secret Buddhist sitting
in this
room it's possible everybody in this
room is Buddha except G
Michael and they are allow
Michael to teach so that maybe he will
listen to
himself but it's also possible there are
some demons in this
room and they are hoping that you don't
give the other person the first CH they
are
hoping then when you give the first
churo to somebody else at lunch today
I hope you
have then you are punching the demon in
the head it's so
fun yeah there's probably some Demon
here then you say oh hi you take the
first that it's like you punch a demon
in the
head they're like ah he gave me the
first
chal he wasn't asleep in the
class we have to put people to sleep all
right number
seven uh think about how much fun it is
to take care of other people
[Music]
first and you just have have to get a
taste of it we call rasa right rasa you
just have to taste
it it's so fun to take care of other
people
Qui and you can have a whole lifetime of
fun so I don't know my teacher taught me
this 50 years
[Music]
ago exactly 50 years
ago I'm trying try to give other people
the first churo for 50 years I don't
always
succeed but it's it's a it made my whole
life
fun so just
try all right Tim when am I supposed to
shut up and huh how
much 13 more minutes okay all right well
take a break in 13
minutes
13 yes 3 I don't know Marina says four
but she says 13
so 13 what time of day am I supposed to
stop this
class
8:3 8:32 8:15 okay good all right let's
go then we'll take a 15 minute
break 30 minute
break oh that's enough to have two
churos okay number number
eight learn to exchange yourself and
others uh this is a very deep
practice it is not what it sounds
like it sounds like uh in English we say
I should put myself in your
[Music]
shoes like I'm up here
teaching then if I'm a good
person
I'm supposed to think about how does H
feel am I speaking too
fast am I using strange
words am I not being logical he cannot
guess what's
next then I have to think about
him and that feels like exchanging
myself and hustle
I put myself on the other half of the
cast my body is on the right side of the
couch from my
viewpoint and his body is on the left
side of the
C so to put in English we say put
yourself in
hiso
how does it feel to be the translator
this
morning that is that what Shan
Tau no it's only
half it's only
half what's what's the
rest in the classic exchanging self and
others of
Shanti
and
there's two
steps number one I have to put my mind
in H's
body I have to feel how does he feel to
be translated this
morning but the second
half I have to look at
and see how does he treat
people that's important second half of
this
practice I'll say it again this practice
number
eight it really has two
parts number one is
obvious I should put my mind inside of
H's body
and then I should think about is it easy
for him to translate in I speaking
clearly like
that but the second half of that
exchange I put myself in H's body and
then I look
at
how does he treat other
people and That's essential second part
of this
practice is he nice to other
people is he bad to other
people you want to go
deeper see is different right in in
Taiwan Taiwan no in Taiwan I taught them
it's okay every country
different there's three kinds of the
exchange uh and it depends on your
position with the other
person for example at your work
is this person your
supervisor does this person work for
you or are you colleagues are you
peers okay and we'll go we'll do that
when we get to it we're not there yet
okay okay number
nine means there's number nine is love
but there's two different
kinds
cha
uh this kind of love is called I want
you to have
something I'll say it again there's two
kinds of
Love uh one is where you want the other
person to have something beautiful
something
nice and that's the emphasis on number
nine what's the other kind of
love I think
protection okay good uh okay number
nine
if you reach number nine and you want
other people to have happiness then you
will start to do
$1 the word is here the word is I should
translate yeah so
because yeah number number nine is
love and it's a love where you give
somebody else
happiness okay and there's a special
word for
that anyway I'll tell you it's the tong
of
Tong okay so there's a bridge
here
love not
compassion love is number
nine that's where you want to give
something nice to somebody
else
and that's called theong
of is a practice it's a
pray it's a breathing
practice and your breath is closely
related to your mental
state if you can control your
breath
you can control your
mental you know when you feel
upset slow down TR try to breathe
slower you
know
this breath
practice so for number
nine it's connected to a breathing
practice and that breathing practice is
called
Tong giving and taking giving and
picking give other people nice
things take away their
problems in your
imagination okay on your breath
uh it's very
cool I used to uh commute two hours to
work each
way 19
years four hours in the bus every
day okay and then that when I get out of
the bus I have to get in the
subway and New York Subway is
dangerous you know and everyone's like
this you
know you know and I and that it's
strange because the seats face each
other so you're
like and then I used to do tongland
every morning on the sun you
know I'm
like then they're
like like that and it's a lot of fun
okay this guy is a he's all nervous he's
going to work you
know then I'm like
probably thinks I'm on cocaine or
something so you can do Tong L with
other
people and it's a it's a secret
practice you don't have to tell
anybody you can just
like you can pretend you have a colder
than
okay so it's a very profound number
nine because you are
using your broken human body to love
other
people and it changes your
body it changes your health by the
way is uh my wife is a massage therapist
we met each other 53 years
ago and people ask
her she has many cancer patients she
gives them
[Music]
mass by the way she charges a
lot last week the lady gave her three
chicken
eggs
for for two and a half hour
Mass I'm like honey it can't takes
gasoline to drive to her
house you can't put the chicken eggs in
the gasoline
[Music]
tent she's like don't worry it'll be
okay
then someone asked
her if you massage a cancer
patient doesn't the cancer vibration get
into your
[Music]
body and she laughed she said no it's
the
opposite when you massage the cancer
patient when you do tongue land when you
give to
you get super
energy pure beautiful energy
filter and if you know her you know she
has this
energy